Preliminary Inventory of the Corinne Lathrop Gilb papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Corinne Lathrop Gilb papers
1945-2005
2007C28
Gilb, Corinne Lathrop, 1925-
220 manuscript boxes. (88 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection contains correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, studies, reports, teaching and research materials, and printed matter, relating to political science, interdisciplinary approaches to American and world history, the history of law, urban history, the history of automobile and high technology industries, and city planning in Detroit.
Administrative Information
Access
Box 83 Closed. Use copies of the materials in Box 84. The remainer of the collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography
Corinne Lathrop Gilb (1925 - 2003) received her Ph.D. in the History of American Civilization from Radcliffe- Harvard and taught history at the university level for 37 years, retiring as Professor Emeritus from Wayne State University in 1994. The first director of UC Berkeley's Regional Cultural (Oral) History Project, her interviews with early Teamster leaders and key figures in the 1934 San Francisco labor strike remain seminal research sources in libraries throughout the country. As Planning Director for the City of Detroit under Mayor Coleman Young, she produced the 1985 Master Plan for the City's future. She also served as consultant to the California legislature, delegate to NGO meetings at the United Nations, and Vice President of the International Society for the Comparative Study of Civilizations. A dynamic public speaker who had an international following, Dr. Gilb is best known as the author of Hidden Hierarchies: The Professions and Government. Selections of her other writings can be found in Toward Holistic History: The Odyssey of an Interdisciplinary Historian, published by Atherton Press.
Selected text from http://corinnelathropgilb.com
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, studies, reports, teaching and research materials, and printed matter, relating to political science, interdisciplinary approaches to American and world history, the history of law, urban history, the history of automobile and high technology industries, and city planning in Detroit.
Organized into groups, the materials include biographical information, Detroit, Michigan materials, speeches and papers, writings, writings conversion project, and collected materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Political science.; History.; United States--Civilization.; Law--History.; Cities and towns--History.; Automobile industry and trade--United States.; High technology industries--United States.; City planning--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.) History.
Collection Contents
- Biographical Information.
  CL Gilb's Chronological History
  - CV's (Folder 55-58)
  - early life (creative writings from the Univ. of Washington), Radcliffe/Harvard Doctor of Philosophy in the History of American Civilization (Folder 55-58)
  - letters between CL Gilb and faculty advisors, original copy of CL Gilb doctoral thesis "Self-Regulating Professions and the Public Welfare: a Case Study of the California State Bar" (May 1956) (Folder 55-58)
  - MA degree in Department of History and special studies at Boalt School of Law at UC Berkeley (Folder 55-58)
  - letters re CL Gilb articles on law and on taxes for the California Legislature (Folder 55-58)
  - Berkeley/California politics 1950's and 60's (Folder 55-58)
  - CDC (Folder 55-58)
  - ADA (Folder 55-58)
  - Berkeley-Albany 1960 Kennedy-Johnson Presidential Campaign (CL Gilb was committee chairman) (Folder 55-58)
  - California Professors for Johnson-Humphrey 1964 (CL Gilb was "coordinator") (Folder 55-58)
  - Berkeley Democratic Club (CL Gilb was President c.1959) (Folder 55-58)
  - Stanley Mosk (California State Attorney General) correspondence with CL Gilb (Folder 55-58)
  - Peter H. Odegard correspondence with CL Gilb (Folder 55-58)
  - 1960s 70s and 80s gen. politics including correspondences with Governor Edmund G. Brown, President Clark Kerr (re 1964 Berkeley), Walter Mondale, Senator Nicholas Petris, Senator Hubert H. Humphrey (Folder 55-58)
  - Adlai Stevenson letter to CL Gilb (after losing 1952 presidential campaign), CL Gilb letter to Senator Ted Kennedy (1976) and CL Gilb photo with Ted Kennedy and Congressman Jeffrey Cohelan (c. 1960) (Folder 55-58)
  - UC Berkeley Bancroft Oral History project (CL Gilb was the first director): lists of her oral histories, papers on the process of oral history writing, letters, CLG notes on "General West Coast Labor Relations as Seen by Employers' Representatives", drafts of other materials (Folder 49-51)
    [***transcripts of her other oral histories were donated to the San Francisco State University Labor Archives and the Institute of Industrial Relations at UC Berkeley]
  - W. Stull Holt correspondence (Folder 49-51)
  - professional associations (Folder 49-51)
  - Social Science Research Council grant (Folder 49-51)
  - Seymour Martin Lipset article and info (Folder 49-51)
  - Institute of Industrial Relations (associate) (Folder 49-51)
  - Mills College (instructor) (Folder 49-51)
  - JFK visit to Mills College (CL Gilb made all arrangements) (Folder 49-51)
  - UC Extension course "Party Politics and Political Leadership", multiple lecturers (CL Gilb "coordinator") (Folder 49-51)
  - Center for Study of Law and Society (associate) (Folder 49-51)
  - Peace Corps (instructor) (Folder 49-51)
  - 1963 world tour, itinerary and pamphlets (Folder 49-51)
  - Wenner-Gren seminars on creativity (participant over two year span) (Folder 49-51)
  - Edward Lurie paper and correspondence w/CL Gilb (Folder 18-21)
  - San Francisco State (instructor) (Folder 18-21)
  - publication of CL Gilb first book Hidden Hierarchies, letters (Folder 18-21)
  - correspondence w/ Harper and Row editors (Folder 18-21)
  - Values in America (unpublished) correspondence w/Knopf editors (Folder 18-21)
  - Ralph Nader letter to CL Gilb (Folder 18-21)
  - CL Gilb testifying to US Senate (Folder 18-21)
  - Guggenheim fellowship 1967 (for Paris and Yugoslavia 1968) (Folder 18-21)
  - Wayne State University (professorship beginning fall 1968, retired emeritus 1994) (Folder 18-21)
  - Bertram Gross correspondence and papers (Folder 18-21)
  - Consciousness in Self and Society, 1975, conference (Folder 18-21)
  - Ralph Pezda (her student) letters and papers (Folder 18-21)
  - Detroit Planning Director (empty folder, see other Detroit boxes) (Folder 18-21)
  - Radcliffe externship program (Folder 18-21)
  - Marshall Gates (destitute boy she tried to help) (Folder 18-21)
  - Handbook of Organizational Design (correspondence, CL Gilb contributed one chapter) (Folder 18-21)
  - International Society for the Comparative Study of Civilization (ISCSC): letters, papers, conference materials (CL Gilb was vice-president several terms), The Comparative Civilizations Review (Folder 99-102)
  - papers by Matthew Melko (ISCSC) (Folder 99-102)
  - papers by Stedman B. Noble (ISCSC) (Folder 99-102)
  - papers by John K. Hord (ISCSC), and other members of ISCSC (Folder 99-102)
  - Stanford/Hoover Visiting Scholar 1993 (Folder 99-102)
  - Silicon Valley Defense/Space Consortium and Silicon Valley Global Trading Center 1995 CEO breakfast speeches (CL Gilb did write-ups) (Folder 99-102)
  - misc. correspondences re politics (Folder 99-102)
  - United Nations: International Organization for Unification of Terminological Neologisms (NGO, CL Gilb a representative) (Folder 99-102)
  - People to People International Citizen Ambassador Program (CL Gilb and husband Tyrell T. Gilb) (Folder 99-102)
  - Atherton Press, Ltd. (CL Gilb founder and president): Roger Williams Wescott correspondence re Atherton Press publication of Comparing Civilizations: an Unconsensual View (Folder 99-102)
  - Boris S. Erasov correspondence re Atherton Press publication of Holding Russia Together (Folder 99-102)
  - Los Altos Town Crier review (9/14/05) of 2005 hardbound publication of Toward Holistic History by Corinne Lathrop Gilb. (Folder 99-102)
  - CL Gilb handwritten travel journals (to China, Russia, Jordan, Tokyo, and Africa) (Folder 83)
  - Use Copies, CL Gilb handwritten travel journals (to China, Russia, Jordan, Tokyo, and Africa) (Folder 84)
  - Day books, address books, membership cards (photocopies), journals/travel notes (unbound) (Folder 67)
  - Professional letters - seeking work, critiques of CL Gilb writings, requests for CL Gilb writings (Folder 22-23)
  - Conferences and travel brochures and information (Folder 39-41)
- Detroit, Michigan Materials
  - CL Gilb's original handwritten "Diary of a Planning Director" (4 volumes) and additional handwritten notes on Detroit/planning (Folder 83)
  - Use copies, Diary of a Planning Director (4 volumes) and additional handwritten notes on Detroit/planning (Folder 84)
  - Papers and speeches on Detroit (Folder 94-95)
  - Detroit news articles on CL Gilb (Folder 94-95)
  - Notes for papers on Detroit, generally during period she was Planning Director for Detroit, 1979-1985 (Folder 94-95)
  - Wayne State University, Detroit. CL Gilb was a professor in the History Department from 1968-1994, then emeritus, as well as Co-Director of the Liberal Arts Urban Studies Program. Includes student evaluations and letters and requests for leave of absence (Folder 7-9)
  - Detroit (1979-1985, when CL Gilb was Planning Director). Contains pamphlets, talks, reports on planning department activities, section list of Detroit Master Plan by CL Gilb, news articles; Coleman Young (including book of quotes and comics about); Joyce Garrett; letters to and from CL Gilb re planning. Note: CL Gilb sent most of her Detroit planning materials to the Burton Collection of the Detroit Public Library - general list of those materials is included in this box. (Folder 10-11)
  - Planning Department letters, press, announcements (Folder 70-73)
  - City publications (Folder 24)
  - Detroit Master Plan
    - Early Detroit master plans (Folder 34-35)
    - Sector master plans (Folder 36-38)
- Speeches and papers
  - A through G (Folder 15-17)
  - H through P (Folder 52-54)
  - R through T, partial (Folder 12-14)
  - T through Z (Folder 46-48)
- Writings
  - World's Earliest Cities. Printouts done by Estate from CL Gilb computer files. (Folder 85-86)
  - Space, Time and the American Pyramid (Folder 25-26)
  - Space, Time and Changing American Values (Folder 25-26)
  - American Values (Folder 25-26)
  - Personal Identity, Space, Time and the American Power Structure (Folder 25-26)
  - Pamphlets, books and magazines in which CL Gilb contributed writings (Folder 42-45)
  - Continuation of pamphlets, books and magazines in which CL Gilb contributed writings (Folder 60-63)
  - Hidden Hierarchies
    - Early drafts (Folder 153-155,192-195)
    - Early drafts plus a copy of Harper and Row and Greenwood Press editions of Hidden Hierarchies (Folder 210-213)
  - Toward Holistic History. Original 2000 softbound edition and early drafts and a copy of the book (Folder 74-76)
  - Master's thesis drafts (from UC Berkeley) and Ph.D. thesis drafts (from Radcliffe), letters (Folder 158-159)
  - Research on writings on law; reports to California State Legislature; [CLG was a special student at Boalt Law School at UC Berkeley in the 1950's] (Folder 196-198)
  - American Values and related titles, unpublished. Includes drafts and notes (Folder 80-82)
  - American Values. Includes drafts and notes (Folder 29-30)
  - American Values, and Space, Time and Rhythm. Includes unpublished related titles and drafts of different books titled with these themes (Folder 87-89)
- Writings
  - World's Earliest Cities (Folder 123-124, 136-138, 142-143)
  - Prelude to Globalism (Folder 160-163)
  - Changing Space of Power (Folder 109-111)
  - Global Hi Tech: View from Detroit. There were many other names for this project comparing the automobile and Silicon Valley industries. In the boxes, it is listed as the "Auto book"
    - Incomplete printouts done by Estate from CL Gilb computer files. (Folder 85-86)
    - Table of Contents (several versions), drafts, and technology research (Folder 106-108)
    - Partial manuscripts (also known as A Century of American Transformations) (Folder 214-215)
    - Loose papers, drafts, notes (Folder 112-114)
    - Research materials and drafts (Folder 96-98, 133-135)
    - Research materials (Folder 117-118, 130-132)
  - Miscellaneous, partial manuscripts, drafts and research (Folder 31-33, 64-66, 77-79,103-105)
  - CD's, tapes, floppies, discs of writings and research (Folder 27-28, 90-93)
- Writings Conversion Project.
  Printouts made by the estate, after CL Gilb's death, of her files of her original writings and research, found on her older computer (requiring conversion from Word Perfect to Word --the discs are included with the files).
  - Notes on the conversion project and bibliographies (Folder 169-171)
  - Bibliographies (Folder 164-165)
  - Prelude to Globalism
    - volume one (Folder 147-149)
    - volume two (Folder 175-177, 178-179)
    - volume three and four (Folder 172-174)
  - Toward Holistic History essays and other written materials (Folder 166-168)
  - Miscellaneous writings on cities, European histories, and bibliographies (Folder 194-186)
  - Research and drafts on world history through study of history of cities (Folder 128-129)
- Teaching materials
  - Class notes
    - History courses (Folder 150-152)
    - Humanities courses (Folder 187-188)
    - Humanities courses (Folder 144-146)
    - Cities courses (Folder 189-191)
    - Urban studies and history (Folder 207-209)
  - Historiography, architecture, science, fiction, symbols, etc. (Folder 204-206)
- Collected Materials
  - Books, pamphlets and handouts re women's studies/feminism, from UC Berkeley area and Wayne State University area, 1970s (Folder 59)
  - Collected materials from the student uprising in Paris, May 1968 (Folder 1-6)
  - California political ephemera (Folder 1-6)
  - Kennedy-Johnson campaign materials, 1960 (Folder 1-6)
  - Collected newspapers and publications (Folder 1-6)